Guide to the Charlie Cobb Interviews, 2012-2013 RL.11333
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charlie Cobb Interviews
2012-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cobb, Charles E., Jr.
RL.11333
98 Files 85 audio files (MP3), 13 document files (Microsoft Word)
3.04 Gigabytes
Audio interviews and programs recorded by Charles E. Cobb, Jr., from 2012 to 2014, with members of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and others around the 50th anniversary of Freedom Summer and for research for Cobb's book, THIS NONVIOLENT STUFF'LL GET YOU KILLED: HOW GUNS MADE THE CIVIL RIGHTS MOVEMENT POSSIBLE.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
The items in this collection are in digital formats. Please contact Research Services staff to arrange access.
Provenance
The Charlie Cobb interviews were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Collection Overview
Audio interviews and programs recorded by Charles E. Cobb, Jr., from 2012 to 2014, with members of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and others around the 50th anniversary of Freedom Summer and for research for Cobb's book, THIS NONVIOLENT STUFF'LL GET YOU KILLED: HOW GUNS MADE THE CIVIL RIGHTS MOVEMENT POSSIBLE. Transcripts are available for a portion of the interviews. Interviewees and speakers include: Shawn Leigh Alexander, Carol Anderson, Annie Pearl Avery, Willie Blue, Julian Bond, Simeon Booker, Taylor Branch, Fred Brooks, Patricia Ann Brooks, Dorothy Burlage, Jackie Byrd, Clayborne Carson, Hodding Carter, the Chinn Family, Purcell Conway, Mac Cotton, Courtland Cox, Connie Curry, Dave Dennis, John Dittmer, John Doar, Ivanhoe Donaldson, LC Dorsey, Myrlie Evers, George Greene, Carol Hallstrom, Vincent Harding, Jessie Harris, Don Harris, Bruce Hartford, Charles Jones, Lonnie King, Dorie Ladner, Bernard Lafayette, Jim Lawson, Worth Long, Deborah Well McCoy, Chuck McDew, Charles McLaurin, Leslie Mclemore, Bob Moses, Christopher Parker, Willie Peacock, Bernice Reagon, Willie Ricks, Reggie Robinson, Cleve Sellers,Charles and Shirley Sherrod, Jane Stembridge, Patricia Sullivan, Flukie Swarez, Corey Walker, and Hollis Watkins. Topics include: civil rights, SNCC, non-violence, guns, and the backgrounds of interview participants.
Biographical note
Charles E. Cobb, Jr., was born in Washington D.C. in 1943. He became active in the Civil Rights Movement while studying at Howard University, and in 1962 traveled to Mississippi, where he was a field secretary for the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee. In 1963, Cobb advocated for Freedom Schools as a way to develop political awareness and involvement by African Americans in Mississippi. After leaving Mississippi in 1967, Cobb helped found the Washington D.C. bookstore Drum and Spear, continued his efforts in African American education with the Center for Black Education, and began a long career in journalism, working for WHUR Radio, National Public Radio, Frontline, and National Geographic. Cobb has been a visiting professor of Africana studies at Brown University, an analyst for allAfrica.com, and is a founding member, and hall of fame inductee, of the National Association of Black Journalists.
Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Mississippi Freedom Project; Civil rights movements -- Southern States; African American; African Americans -- Civil rights; African Americans -- Civil rights -- History; African Americans -- Civil rights -- Mississippi -- History -- 20th century; Audiovisual materials; Digital audio formats; Oral histories (document genre); Firearms ownership--United States; Cobb, Charles E., Jr.; Alexander, Shawn Leigh; Anderson, Carol, 1937-; Avery, Annie Pearl, 1943-; Blue, Willie; Bond, Julian, 1940-2015; Booker, Simeon, 1918-; Branch, Taylor; Brooks, Fred, 1928-; Brooks, Patricia Ann; Burlage, Dorothy Dawson; Byrd, Jackie; Carson, Clayborne, 1944-; Carter, Hodding; Chinn, C.O.; Conway, Purcell Maurice, 1948-; Cotton, Mac; Cox, Courtland, 1941-; Curry, Constance, 1933-; Dennis, Dave; Dittmer, John, 1939-; Doar, John, 1921-2014; Donaldson, Ivanhoe; Dorsey, L. C. (Lula Clara Warren), 1938-; Evers-Williams, Myrlie; Greene, George; Hallstrom, Carol; Harding, Vincent; Harris, Donald (Donald Stuart); Harris, Jessie; Hartford, Bruce (Civil rights activist); Jones, Charles, 1937-; King, Lonnie C., 1936-; Ladner, Dorie; LaFayette, Bernard, Jr.; Lawson, James M., 1928-; Long, Worth W.; McCoy, Deborah Well; McDew, Charles; McLaurin, Charles; McLemore, Leslie Burl; Moses, Robert Parris; Parker, Christopher S., 1963-; Peacock, Wazir; Reagon, Bernice Johnson, 1942-; Ricks, Willie Floyd; Robinson, Reggie; Sellers, Cleveland, 1944-; Sherrod, Charles, 1937-; Sherrod, Shirley, 1948-; Stembridge, Jane; Suarez, Mateo "Flukie"; Sullivan, Patricia, 1950-; Walker, Corey D. B.; Watkins, Hollis, 1941-
- Brown University Interviews, 2014; 1
  - Avery, Annie Pearl, 2014-11-06; 1
    - Brown Oral History 20141106 Annie Pearl Interview.mp3, 0:59:40 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
      Scope and Contents
      Discussing growing up in Birmingham (partially) then moved to Pittsburgh for a while then back to Birmingham at 14yrs old (late 50s) and the trauma from that. Discussed the turmoil/racial unrest in the south that surrounded the late 50s, how she got involved in the movement, she heard about the freedom riders she bought a ticket from Birmingham to Montgomery, met Wilson Brown at the Greyhound station, Wilson brown explained nonviolence and she decided she didn't want to do it so she got a refund on her ticket, Wilson invited her to a SNCC meeting in Atlanta, she went to the meeting with Nathaniel Lee and Wilson Brown. At the meeting she met Julian, Reggie, Bob Mants, Diane Nash, Anne and Carl Braden, Bob Zellner & Ella Baker. Discussed Marietta GA incident and almost getting killed on the way back to Birmingham. Attempting to meet Rev Shuttlesworth in Birmingham and the white girl was with them and they asked for directions in Marietta and people spotted them and had them followed by police. Wilson is in jail, Annie and the white girl started looking for black people, they went back to the bus station, bought tickets back to Atlanta, Nathaniel had a number and he called the SNCC office. The Associated Press started calling after Nathaniel called the SNCC office in Atlanta and asked if they were alright. A mob had gathered and they were beating on the seats. Howard Moore (attorney), Julian and someone else in a black car and they lead them back to Atlanta, Forman suggested they stay in Atlanta the night then went to Rev Shuttlesworth house (Birmingham), After this, Annie begins going to the mass meetings. Rev Shuttlesworth, Pfeiffer, Willis, Billups and Oliver part of the movement in Birmingham. Went to the second Atlanta conference, then she went down to Albany GA to demonstrate on Bob's request, she was arrested for the first time there. Participated in sit ins in Birmingham, Gaston, AL, Discussed what did family/friends think about her involvement in movement (appeared happy), thought it was dangerous, discussed the different places she worked in the movement on and thoughts on guns.
  - Cotton, Mac, 2014-11-03; 2
    - Brown Oral History 20141103 Mac Interview Audio.mp3, 0:46:50 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
      From Kosciusko, discussed how family reacted to his movement work, MS, Discussed attending Tougaloo College and movement beginnings there. Bob Moses asked Mac to go to McComb County then he went Wallflower County (MS).Discussed his movement experiences in Wallflower, secret black society in Wallflower that protected community, the community's reaction to SNCC, discussed working in the Mississippi Delta. Attitudes about black people in Hill country had about plantation country in the Delta.
  - Hallstrom, Carol, 2014-11-04; 3
    - Brown Oral History 20141104 Carol Hallstrom Interview Audio.mp3, 0:51:39 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
      Charlie asks Carol to discuss how she got interested in the movement with her background. Carol explains her history of her family's experience with persecution & having to flee Russia, Ukraine (Jews) and when she heard about the Greensboro sit ins their courage struck her to be involved. Carol discusses her beginning in the movement, she connected with those in Philadelphia and coordinate efforts to go into Baltimore. Discussing integrating restaurants, Recalling her first arrest which was in Cambridge, how she was ostracized by the college community who found her involvement embarrassing, Encountered SNCC through Reggie Robinson, Discussed Gloria Richardson who lead CNAC (Cambridge Nonviolent Action Committee), Also worked in New York SNCC office identifying people who could support the organization, Carol took an integrated group of high school students by bus down to Amite County(Spring 64) to expose them to how it was in the area, discusses how ended up working as a field secretary in Amite County (through Mr. Steptoe), work in Amite County, guns and complications of being a white woman from Brooklyn, NY traveling with Herbert lee Jr and E.W Steptoe in Mississippi (she said she had to be willing to listen to listen more than talk), had to be willing to not talk, taking chances rather than talking about taking chances, discussed Andy Goodman (She's the one who recruited him). Discussed how Amite County whites reacted to her presence (negatively). Ended with discussing leaving Amite County.
  - Long, Worth, 2014-11-05; 4
    - Brown Oral History 20141105 Worth Interview Audio.mp3, 1:04:18 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
      Discussing his beginnings in the movement in Arkansas (ARSNCC) and becoming a member of the SNCC staff, the term unviolence, 1960 Raleigh conference, local people and their use of unviolence, Hartman Turnbow( Holmes County), Worth discusses his role as field secretary in SNCC, He gets to Selma, AL because couldn't get anyone else to go so he signed up, taking refuge with the nation of Islam temple, getting arrested and beat up. Discussing how the local people felt towards SNCC: those of the status quo didn't receive them well, others appreciated SNCC.
  - Ricks, Willie, 2014-11-04; 5
    - Brown Oral History 20141104 Willie Riks Interview Audio.mp3, 0:58:57 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
      Coined the term black power, discussed: The march/rally when which Black Power was first said, The issues between SNCC and SCLC, Growing up in Chattanooga, TN, Freedom Riders/Fred Winter came through Chattanooga (that's how he first got involved with movement), getting arrested in the sit ins, intimidation for local whites, Discussed hearing of SNCC in 1963 and how Ruby Doris Smith called on him to work for SNCC in Atlanta (1963), Also the movement work he did in Gaston AL, Birmingham AL, then was assigned to SW Georgia (until Selma). Discussed first time using "Black Power", Discussed his pan Africanism and back to Africa ideas.
  - Robinson, Reggie, 2014-11-05; 6
    - Brown Oral History 20141105 Reggie Interview Audio.mp3, 0:53:09 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
      Discussing his involvement Civil Interest group (affiliated to SNCC), after dropping out of high school, he went to Cortez Peters business college, Dean of his school Walter Dixon (first black city council Baltimore), Dixon asked Reggie to become a part of the student group (Civil Interest group), Dixon introduced a public accommodations bill and Reggie was the eyes/ears of the student interest group, became treasurer of the Civil Interest group, Voter Registration(preparing people for the voter registration tests), Discussed how he became the representative for SNCC for the big Kentucky meeting, and how he was presented by Ella Baker at the Kentucky meeting. Reggie was asked to go to Mississippi (McComb). Discussed staying at Mama Cotton's house in McComb, setting up freedom school, Voter registration tests in Mississippi, SNCC's first tragedy: the murder of Herbert Lee, SNCC got scared and Amzie Moore convinced them to stay and they turned the funeral into a mass meeting and continued to do work. Situation had gotten out of hand and they had gotten back to Atlanta regrouped and decided who would go back to Mississippi.
  - Group audio, 2014-11-03; 7
    - Brown Oral History 20141103 Group Audio.mp3, 1:48:41 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
  - Group audio, 2014-11-04; 8
    - Brown Oral History 20141104 Group Audio.mp3, 1:55:19 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
  - Group audio, 2014-11-05; 9
    - Brown Oral History 20141105 Group Audio.mp3, 2:01:16 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
  - Group audio, 2014-11-06; 10
    - Brown Oral History 20141106 Group Audio.mp3, 1:50:49 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0001)
- Mississippi Freedom Summer 50th Anniversary Conference Interviews, 2013; 2
  - Blue, Willie, 2013-10-16; 11
    - rev. Willie Blue.mp3, 0:10:50 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0002)
  - Cotton, Mac, 2013-10-15; 12
    - Mac Cotton.mp3, 0:25:52 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0002)
  - Greene, George, 2013-10-16; 13
    - George Greene.mp3, 0:37:16 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0002)
  - Harris, Jessie, 2013-10-15; 14
    - Jessie Harris.mp3, 0:39:55 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0002)
  - McLaurin, Charles, 2013-10-16; 15
    - Charles McLaurin.mp3, 0:37:49 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0002)
  - Mclemore, Leslie, 2013-10-17; 16
    - Leslie Mclemore.mp3, 0:36:37 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0002)
  - Watkins, Hollis, 2013-10-16; 17
    - Hollis Watkins.mp3, 0:29:58 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0002)
- This Nonviolent Stuff Will Get You Killed Interviews, 2012-2013; 3
  - Alexander, Shawn Leigh, undated; 18
    - pp_podcast_alexander.mp3, 0:20:40 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      University of Pennsylvania Press podcast. Stephanie Brown interviews with Shawn Leigh Alexander on his book Army of Lions.
  - Anderson, Carol, 2012-09-11; 19
    - Carol Andersn 09112012.mp3, 0:55:35 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      (Poor quality). Discussing inner conflicts blacks had in fighting in WW2 when freedom wasn't available at home. Black men came home and protected home with military precision. To arm or not? You can't give something that's already ours, you can only take. Role of the veteran in the movement.
  - Bond, Julian, 2012-10-12; 20
    - Julian Bond October 12 2012.mp3, 0:39:05 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Charlie asks Julian about the founding SNCC conference in 1960. Discussed: feelings about nonviolence, experience with guns, Discussed the conversations SNCC as an organization had about guns, Local people and their guns.
  - Booker, Simeon, 2013-07-01; 21
    - Simeon Booker July 1 2013.mp3, 0:29:22 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. wife Carol McCabe Booker also. Discussing interviewing in the south with the danger, Discussed Amzie Moore (one of his best contacts in MS), Aaron Moore, Medgar Evers. Discussed what it was like for Johnson Publication to come down to the Deep South. Discussed covering Emmet Till case.
  - Branch, Taylor, 2013-08-13; 22
    - Taylor Branch conversation August 13 2013.mp3, 0:31:39 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Discussed nonviolence and armed self-defense. Also discussed the perceptions of nonviolence, like that it was passive.
  - Brooks, Fred, 2013-06-30; 23
    - Fred Brooks June 30 2013.mp3, 1:12:38 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Klan attacks freedom house in Jonesboro,LA, Deacons for defense
  - Brooks, Patricia Ann, 2013-01-20; 24
    - Patricia Ann Brooks on Columbia Jan 30 2013.mp3, 0:18:09 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. discussed the riot in Columbia TN
  - Burlage, Dorothy, 2013-05-25; 25
    - Dorothy Burlage 1 May 25 2013.mp3, 1:02:05 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview Part 1. Desegregation caused the resurgence of KKK and white citizens council, discussing the white reaction to blacks organizing and being involved in the movement. Discussed movement people. Opinion on nonviolence vs violence. She's a pacifist but not judgmental of those who chose to use weapons.
    - Dorothy Burlage 2 May 25 2013.mp3, 0:07:42 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview Part 2. Short interview, discussing Robert Williams, who he wasn't that different than mainstream, discussed the NAACP was suspicious of Medgar Evers.
  - Byrd, Jackie, 2012-07-20; 26
    - Jackie Byrd in McComb July 20 2012.mp3, 0:19:20 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person/background noise. Recording began in middle of conversation, they are discussing bombings, CC Bryant church bombed, Mr. Bryant brought Bob Moses down to McComb county MS. Bombings began patrols with guns. Also discussed the camaraderie and unique sense of community McComb had. Shortly discussed the "crazy negro" idea and why they were left alone.
  - Carson, Clayborne, 2013-04-11; 27
    - Clayborne Carson April 11 2013.mp3, 0:12:01 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Recording began as talking had already commenced, SNCC wasn't built around a particular viewpoint, except the statement of purpose. Violence vs nonviolence, Believed more in unviolence which is more of self defense.
  - Carter, Hodding, 2012-08-26; 28
    - Hodding Carter Aug 26 2012.mp3, 1:40:15 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Difficult to understand/Carter is muffled. In person. In relation to Charlie Cobb book, Fear of black insurrection comes out of the knowledge of violence done to blacks through years, Beginning of fear of blacks,Self defense,
  - Chinn Family, undated; 29
    - Chinn Family 1.mp3, 1:10:55 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      (Poor quality). A lot of background music/noise. Discussing the atmosphere and environment in Mississippi during the 60s, commentary on modern events, Trayvon Martin, war, C.O Chinn, story of him wearing a pistol in court,
  - Conway, Purcell, 2012-12-06; 30
    - Purcell Conway 1 December 6 2012.mp3, 1:04:01 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person. Palm Coast, Florida. Discusses Purcell's early life in St. Augustine, FL/Lincolnville FL, Conditions in Lincolnville were dismal, Influence from Florida Normal College students to become more aware of movement, nonviolence, Self. defense, Lincolnville was different in that they would protect their own with violence, the whites there normally didn't come into black community to violence but they community responded with violence. Caused whites to be afraid to come into black communities of West Augustine and Lincolnville. Discussing early interest and beginnings of being in the movement, Parents thoughts on the protest/movements, and the racist element followed MLK Jr and severe violence began then. And talks about WW2 veterans including Purcell's father.
    - Purcell Conway 2 December 6 2012.mp3, 0:19:07 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person. Short Interview, discusses racial issues within masonry class in Daytona Beach, firing from working in the Post Office in NY because of racism and having to get an lawyer to get job back and he got the job back.
  - Cotton, Mac, undated; 31
    - mac cotton on SW Mississippi.mp3, 0:13:56 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person. Short Interview on SW Mississippi. Discusses the local people who helped to protect SNCC and Guns.
  - Cox, Courtland, 2013-01-06; 32
    - Courtland Cox part1 Jan 6 2013.mp3, 0:18:19 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person Part 1. In Washington D.C: chronological interview, attended Howard University, A member of NAG/SNCC, did sit ins at Howard, Discussion about non violence, he says people believed it was a good tactical move/strategic, you engaged in non violence because you didn't have enough force to confront the opposition. States Nonviolence appealed to outsiders to address fear. Spoke on NAG. Advantage of nonviolence is it was relatable to the dominate religious narrative, the only way people could understand and not be afraid.
    - Courtland Cox part2 Jan 6 2013.mp3, 1:23:46 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person Part 2. Doesn't think the movement could have survived without the non violent component, allowed the movement to grow. Albany GA and Nashville groups were philosophically nonviolent. Honor roll students in the movement, Sterling Brown: mentor of NAG,not allowed to be a campus organization, talked about Howard University faculty and their relationship with the movement and NAG students. Howard University administration didn't want anything to do with civil rights but didn't condemn students for off campus activity. NAACP resentment towards SNCC and Dr.King.
  - Curry, Connie, 2013-02-09; 33
    - Connie Curry February 9 2013.mp3, 0:22:55 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Recording began after conversation started, discussion of Medgar Evers and his guns, discussion about non violence as a way of life vs tactical non violence. To her knowledge it was never suggested that SNCC accept non violence as a way of life.
  - Dennis, Dave, 2013-04-09; 34
    - Dave Dennis April 9 2013.mp3, 0:43:12 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Providence, Rhode Island at Brown University. In person. discussing Northern Louisiana, Deacons for Defense. Started in Jonesboro, Louisiana. 1957 in Shreveport, LA the first "I have a dream" speech by MLK Jr. Organized with men who worked in paper mills and worked with longshoreman union in New Orleans. CORE group began working with Deacons because they were resistant to outsiders telling locals how to protect their communities. CORE organized in Louisiana around 1960. Dave Dennis went to hometown (Shreveport) to establish CORE there, NAACP was already there. Deacons operated to protect the churches then eventually spread out to protect community as a whole. The Deacons were called by a different name at first. Northern Louisiana: staunch segregation and Klan territory, southwest Louisiana: integrated living, Voter Registration and CORE's involvement.
    - Dave Dennis3 June 23 2012.mp3, 0:28:55 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      Telephone interview. Recording began in middle of conversation: Discussing New Orleans core group members: George, Jerome Smith, Doris Castle held group together and committed were committed to nonviolence through Jim McCain (CORE national chapter). New Orleans group sort of a renegade CORE group. CORE disintegrated after Floyd McKissick was voted in. CORE Louisiana group stopped organizing chapters, started working with local people.
  - Dittmer, John, undated; 35
    - John Dittmer at Fannie Lou Hamerr Institute.mp3, 1:04:34 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      John Dittmer at Fannie Lou Hamer Institute (poor quality). Lecture is mostly focuses on Mississippi and McComb County specifically. Talks about government and voting (specifically the poll taxes, laws and literacy tests that made voting difficult. Briefly discusses the White Citizen's Council. The rest of the lecture is Q & A.
  - Doar, John, 2012-06-26; 36
    - John Doar june 26 2012.mp3, 0:22:48 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)
      In person/background noise/Poor Quality. Talks about meeting Mr. Steptoe, Guns, local people protecting themselves with weapons, tension/violence in the south,
  - Donaldson, Ivanhoe, 2013-04-23; 37
    - Ivanhoe Donaldson1 april 23 2013.mp3, 0:35:32 (Server TTS, E-folder RL11333-LFF-0003)